detma.org 2002-06-04

# MDET:Privacy Policy

This is the Web site of the Massachusetts Division of Employment and Training (DET). Your privacy is one of our top priorities. The following policy applies only to the use of the DET Web site. Other Web sites operated by other Massachusetts state agencies have different policies. We strongly suggest that you read the privacy policies for each Commonwealth Web site that you visit, and any external site that you visit through a link appearing at this site. 

**

A Privacy Partnership 

**

Your privacy with respect to the use of this Web site results from a partnership between DET and you, the user. At this Web site, we attempt to protect your privacy to the maximum extent possible. However, because some of the information that we receive through this Web site is subject to the [Public Records Law (Massachusetts General Laws, Chapter 66, Section 10](http://www.state.ma.us/legis/laws/mgl/66-10.htm)), we cannot ensure absolute privacy. Some information that you provide to us through this site may be made available to members of the public under that law. This policy informs you of the information that we collect from you at this site, what we do with it, to whom it may be disseminated, and how you can access it. Based on this information, you can make an informed choice about your use of this site. You can maximize the benefits of your privacy partnership with DET by making informed choices about whether to share personally identifiable information with us through this site.

**

Personally Identifiable Information

**

When you send an e-mail through this Web site, that e-mail will automatically contain some personally identifiable information. We use the term "personally identifiable information" to mean any information that could reasonably be used to identify you, including your name, address, telephone number, e-mail address, Social Security number, employer business identification number, birth date, bank account information, credit card information, or any combination of information that could be used to identify you. The only personally identifiable information collected by this site would be as a result of an e-mail you send. top

**

Your Privacy and E-mails

**

DET asks that you do not use e-mail to send information that you consider to be confidential. E-mail is not secure and may be intercepted by a third party. If your communication relates to service you have received from DET, is highly sensitive or includes personal information such as your Social Security number or business identification number, we suggest that you call DET or send your message by regular mail. We recognize this creates constraints and regret any inconvenience. DET will be adopting a secure method of Internet communication in the near future. 

In order to maintain your confidentiality, DET will respond by e-mail only to questions of general interest. We will contact you by telephone or regular mail to respond to inquiries about your unemployment insurance claim, employment situation, or business. top

**

Information Automatically Collected and Stored by this Site

**

This Web site does not use "cookies." Cookies are files or small pieces of information that some Web sites place on computers to track your activity on the site or to recognize you when you return to the site. 

However, MassStats – our on-line interactive economic data system – does use a temporary connector. This is necessary because MassStats is designed to allow desktop users to query a central DET database and receive immediate response to those queries at their desktops. In order to know where to send responses to your queries, we must be temporarily connected to your personal computer. 

This connection exists only during the time that you are using MassStats. It contains no personal data, is not stored in any way by DET’s Web site, nor can it be retrieved by DET. Once you stop using MassStats, or turn off your computer, the connection disappears. 

If you choose not to accept this connection, all sections of the DET Web site will still be fully functional, except for MassStats. 

Some of the forms posted on the DET Web site do include text boxes that allow you to complete the forms on-line. These forms, however, cannot be transmitted electronically to DET and this site does not capture any of the information you place on the form. 

This site does collect and store indefinitely your Internet Protocol ("IP") address, which does not identify you as an individual, as well as information about the date and time of your visit, and the DET Web site pages visited. We use your IP address to assess the frequency of visits to this site and the popularity of its various pages and functions. We will not attempt to match any personally identifiable information that you provide to us with your IP address, unless there are reasonable grounds to believe that doing so would provide information that is relevant and material to a criminal investigation. top

**

Confidentiality at DET and the Dissemination of Personally Identifiable Information

**

DET takes seriously its role in protecting the privacy of our customers. Claimants, job seekers, and employers who do business with DET are protected by strict rules of confidentiality. The laws requiring this confidentiality are the _[ Massachusetts Employment and Training Law ](http://www.state.ma.us/legis/laws/mgl/151a-46.htm) _(Massachusetts General Laws, Chapter 151A, Section 46) and _[Massachusetts General Laws, Chapter 23, Section 9L](http://www.state.ma.us/legis/laws/mgl/23-9l.htm)_ under which DET administers its programs. 

**

This means that information held by DET – on individual unemployment insurance claims, job seekers using DET and One-Stop Career Center services, and Massachusetts employers covered by the Massachusetts unemployment insurance law – is confidential and cannot be divulged without the permission of the parties, except under very specific circumstances.

**

Information that you voluntarily submit through an e-mail to this Web site may be shared with DET employees or officials, but only with those authorized employees with a "need to know" for purposes of fulfilling their job responsibilities. Those DET staff members will use the information solely to answer your questions, respond to any requests for assistance, and fulfill our obligations. Any of these e-mails may be retained as a record of service provided or may be archived. 

DET will not disclose any personal or business information we obtain to third parties, unless one of the following limited exceptions applies:  

  * DET may furnish your personal information (provided, for example, when you apply for unemployment benefits in person or by telephone) to other government agencies if required by state or federal law. 

  * Where appropriate, we may provide the information submitted by you to the person or company that is the subject of your inquiry, or to a government agency responsible for the matters referred to in your communication. 

You should still be aware, however, that once you voluntarily submit personally identifiable information to us through an e-mail – and that information does not pertain to a claim for unemployment insurance benefits, an employer’s unemployment insurance tax account or job search activities provided by DET or career center staff – its dissemination is governed by: 

  * the [Public Records Law](http://www.state.ma.us/legis/laws/mgl/66-10.htm) (Massachusetts General Laws, Chapter 66),

  * the _[ Fair Information Practices Act](http://www.state.ma.us/legis/laws/mgl/gl-66A-toc.htm)_ (Massachusetts General Laws, Chapter 66A),

  * [Executive Order 412](http://www.state.ma.us/consumer/New/privexeco.htm), and other applicable laws and regulations.

Because of these laws, DET may be required to provide all or part of the information you send us by e-mail – information that is not covered by the laws governing confidentiality at DET – to a member of the public in response to a public records request.

Finally, DET does not sell any personally identifiable information collected through this Web site. top

**

Links to Other Web Sites

**

The DET Web site contains links to other Web sites such as job search sites, career resource sites, and other government agency sites over which DET has no control. Once you link to these sites, you are no longer on the DET Web site and are subject to the privacy policy of the new site. top

**

Security

**

Because this site does not encrypt incoming e-mail, DET asks that you do not send through e-mail any information that you consider to be highly sensitive or confidential. E-mail is not secure and may be intercepted by a third party. If your communication is in regard to service you have received from DET, is highly sensitive or includes personal information such as your Social Security number, we suggest that you call DET or send your message by regular mail. top

We use standard security measures to ensure that any personally identifiable information is not lost, misused, altered, or unintentionally destroyed. We also use software programs to monitor network traffic to identify unauthorized attempts to upload or change information, or otherwise cause damage. Except for authorized law enforcement investigations, no attempts are made to identify individual users or their usage habits. 

**

Special Protections Against Misuse of Personally Identifiable Information Within Commonwealth Offices

**

In 1999, then-Acting Governor Swift issued [Executive Order 412](http://www.state.ma.us/consumer/New/privexeco.htm), which enhanced the privacy protection given to any information about you as a named individual held by the Executive Department of state government. Executive Order 412 limits the collection and dissemination of personally identifiable information within the Executive Department. This site complies with Executive Order 412, so all of the personally identifiable information that you submit to this site is given the privacy protections set forth in Executive Order 412. top

**

Policy Changes

**

We will post changes to this policy at least 30 days before they take effect. Any information we collect under the current privacy policy will remain subject to the terms of this policy. After any changes take effect, all new information we collect, if any, will be subject to the new policy. top

**

Your Access and Opportunity to Correct

**

The [Public Records Law](http://www.state.ma.us/legis/laws/mgl/66-10.htm) and the [Fair Information Practices Act ](http://www.state.ma.us/legis/laws/mgl/gl-66A-toc.htm)provide you certain rights to get information about you that is in our records. To learn more about the circumstances under which you can get and correct this information, please click on the above references to these laws. top

**

Contact Information

**

For questions, comments and complaints about on-line privacy matters while using this Web site, please contact Maida Shifman, Director of Customer Relations at [mshifman@detma.org](mailto:mshifman@detma.org) or write to Division of Employment and Training, Customer Relations Office, 19 Staniford Street, Boston MA 02114, Attn: Maida Shifman. top

****

**Information** **Disclaimer**

DET provides this Web site as a public service to provide immediate access to DET information.  While DET makes every effort to keep the information on the site accurate, current, and reliable, we can make no guarantees about the accuracy, currency, completeness or adequacy of the contents of this Web site, including any links to other Web sites. As a result, DET expressly disclaims liability for errors and omissions of any kind. If information on this Web site differs from information on an official DET notice and/or publication, the official notice and/or publication take precedence. DET makes no warranty of any kind, implied, express or statutory with regard to this Web site, including its links to other Web sites. top

**

Link Disclaimer

**

DET provides links to other sites simply as a service and a convenience to its customers. Inclusion of links to any reference, referral service, or outside Web site, including job databases and their contents, or the use of any trade name or other business name is solely for the convenience of Web site visitors. It is not intended to reflect their importance and does not constitute an endorsement or recommendation of Web site content, viewpoint, policies, products or services by DET. 

Databases accessible through DET's Mass Job Bank site may contain job listings in which applicants are instructed to apply directly to employers or private placement agencies. DET is not responsible for any arrangements concerning employment interviews or terms of employment made directly between applicants and employers or placement agencies.

The contents and links on this Web site are subject to change without notice. top

**

Definitions:

**

**Cookies** are files that a Web site can place on your computer. A cookie file contains unique information that a Web site can use to track such things as your password, lists of Web pages you have visited, and the date when you last looked at a specific Web page, or to identify your session at a particular Web site. A cookie file allows the Web site to recognize you as you click through pages on the site and when you later revisit the site. A Web site can use cookies to "remember" your preferences, and to record your browsing behavior on the Web. Although you can prevent Web sites from placing cookies on your computer by using your browser's preference menu, disabling cookies may affect your ability to view or interact with some Web sites. 

****

**An "Internet Protocol Address" or "IP Address"** is a series of numbers that identifies each computer and machine connected to the Internet. An IP address enables a server on a computer network to send you the file that you have requested on the Internet. The IP address disclosed to us may identify the computer from which you are accessing the Internet, or a server owned by your Internet Service Provider. Because it is machine-specific, rather than person-specific, an IP address is not, in and of itself, personally identifiable information. top
